{
  "reference_number": "8527",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "To give us the best possibility of achieving no more than 1.5 degrees warming by the end of the century, there must be rapid cuts in\n all greenhouse gases beginning now. I support a net-zero target of 2040 with the majority of cuts occurring over the next decade."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I strongly support the ‘firewall’ principle – that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own emissions, and not\n through the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "To give us the best possibility of achieving no more than 1.5 degrees warming by the end of the century, there must be rapid cuts in\n all greenhouse gases beginning now. I support a net-zero target of 2040 with the majority of cuts occurring over the next decade."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The legislation should establish the goal of limiting warming to 1.5 degrees. We should not settle for 2 degrees warming, that would\n\nlock in devastating impacts on Pacific Island states and cause significant extinctions. That is not acceptable. To give us the best\npossibility of achieving no more than 1.5 degrees warming by the end of the century, there must be rapid cuts in all greenhouse\n\ngases beginning now. I support a net-zero target of 2040 with the majority of cuts occurring over the next decade. I support all\ngreenhouse gases being included in the law, consistent with international climate frameworks. The Intergovernmental Panel on\n\nClimate Change makes it clear that methane reduction is critical to success in tackling climate change. It is politically and scientifically\nuntenable for New Zealand’s climate law to exclude any gases from our biggest emitting sector - the agricultural sector. I support the\nestablishment of a Climate Commission, whose role should be to devise binding budgets. The Climate Commission should have\n\nstatutory teeth, otherwise, it is merely an advisory group that governments could ignore. Climate budgets should be legally binding\nand set a bare-minimum ambition, which must be achieved or bettered by government within the prescribed timeframes. Finally, while\n\nbudgets should be binding, policy recommendations from the Commission should be just that - recommendations. I strongly support\nthe ‘firewall’ principle – that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own emissions, and not through the\n\npurchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks. Regarding our international commitments, the Bill\nmust include a requirement that governments produce annual reports about New Zealand’s international climate change\ncontributions. As a Pacific nation, we must ensure that the Pacific countries get the support they need to adapt to the devastating\n\neffects of climate change and their changing environment – a problem they contributed very little to. Access to climate finance is a\nmatter of justice: those who have contributed least to the causes of the problem are typically the most vulnerable to its impacts and\n\nhave the least resources to respond. New Zealand must demonstrate global leadership and match its bold vision for lower carbon\nemissions at home by having an equally ambitious climate change strategy abroad."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I strongly support the ‘firewall’ principle – that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own emissions, and not\nthrough the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Dear Minister, I support the passing of legally binding climate law and maintain that Climate Change is a global problem – it cannot be\ntackled by countries in isolation. The law must be fair, ambitious and consistent with the climate science and international frameworks\n\nby including all gases and all sectors. The legislation should establish the goal of limiting warming to 1.5 degrees. We should not\nsettle for 2 degrees warming, that would lock in devastating impacts on Pacific Island states and cause significant extinctions. That is\n\nnot acceptable. To give us the best possibility of achieving no more than 1.5 degrees warming by the end of the century, there must\nbe rapid cuts in all greenhouse gases beginning now. I support a net-zero target of 2040 with the majority of cuts occurring over the\n\nnext decade. I support all greenhouse gases being included in the law, consistent with international climate frameworks. The\nIntergovernmental Panel on Climate Change makes it clear that methane reduction is critical to success in tackling climate change. It\nis politically and scientifically untenable for New Zealand’s climate law to exclude any gases from our biggest emitting sector - the\n\nagricultural sector. I support the establishment of a Climate Commission, whose role should be to devise binding budgets. The\nClimate Commission should have statutory teeth, otherwise, it is merely an advisory group that governments could ignore. Climate\n\nbudgets should be legally binding and set a bare-minimum ambition, which must be achieved or bettered by government within the\nprescribed timeframes. Finally, while budgets should be binding, policy recommendations from the Commission should be just that -\n\nrecommendations. I strongly support the ‘firewall’ principle – that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own\nemissions, and not through the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks. Regarding our\ninternational commitments, the Bill must include a requirement that governments produce annual reports about New Zealand’s\n\ninternational climate change contributions. As a Pacific nation, we must ensure that the Pacific countries get the support they need to\nadapt to the devastating effects of climate change and their changing environment – a problem they contributed very little to. Access\n\nto climate finance is a matter of justice: those who have contributed least to the causes of the problem are typically the most\nvulnerable to its impacts and have the least resources to respond. New Zealand must demonstrate global leadership and match its\n\nbold vision for lower carbon emissions at home by having an equally ambitious climate change strategy abroad. While consensus\nacross political parties is preferred, any cross-party agreement should not be achieved at the cost of strong climate law. Climate\n\nchange is the greatest challenge facing humanity. It would be wrong to have broad agreement on weak law, when what is urgently\nneeded to address the problem is strong law. The world needs pathways to transformational change if we are to avoid catastrophic\nwarming. This is the scale of the challenge. The science is clear: the only way we can succeed is with big ambition. New Zealand\nmust be bold and pass strong law for the sake of our precious earth and future generations. Nga Mihi Artur Francisco"
    }
  ]
}
